Guide to the Charles S. Jackson Family Photographs Collection 1880-1951
Oregon Historical Society, Research Library
Charles S. Jackson Family Photographs Collection
1880-1951
1900-1930
Oregon Historical Society, Davies Family Research Library Research Library 1200 SW Park Avenue Portland, Oregon 97205 Phone: 503-306-5240 Fax: 503-219-2040 E-mail: libreference@ohs.org
Org. Lot 36
Jackson, Charles Samuel, 1860-1924
1 cubic foot 150 photographs in 1 box and 4 oversize folders
The collection contains photographs of newspaper owner Charles Samuel Jackson of Pendleton and Portland, Or., his family, and his newspaper enterprises, including the East Oregonian and Oregon Journal.
Biographical Note
Charles Samuel A. (Sam) Jackson (1860-1924) was born in Virginia and moved to Pendleton, Oregon, in the early 1880s. He gradually acquired ownership of the East Oregonian newspaper. He married native Virginian, Maria Clopton (1862-1956), in Pendleton in 1886. They had two sons, Francis Clopton Jackson (1887-1919) and Phillip Ludwell Jackson (1893-1953).
In 1902, Sam Jackson moved to Portland and acquired the newly established Oregon Journal, an evening newspaper which he promoted as a civic-minded people's newspaper. The paper's success necessitated building new quarters at Broadway and Yamhill in 1912, a location which was itself subsequently outgrown. In 1948, the Journal relocated to the former Public Market building on Front Street between Yamhill and Taylor.
Maria Jackson was active in civic and Episcopal Church affairs. The family home on Salmon Street became the site of the clubhouse for the Portland Federation of Women's Clubs. The Jacksons' son, Phillip, and their grandson, C. S. Jackson, II (1914-1947), were active in management of the Oregon Journal and other family enterprises. In addition to their Portland home, the family built a log lodge on Clear Creek near Carver, Oregon.
This collection contains photographs relating to Charles S. Jackson and his family. Some of the photographs are portraits and informal photographs of Jackson, his wife, Maria Clopton Jackson, and their sons, Francis Clopton Jackson and Phillip Ludwell Jackson, among other family members, including a series of photographs depicting Francis' service with the Merchant Marines and Phillip's with the U.S. Army during World War I. There are also photographs of the buildings, activities, and employees of the East Oregonian in Pendleton and the Oregon Journal in Portland, including photographs detailing the construction of the Oregon Journal building in 1912. Photographers include Walter Boychuk and Angelus Studio in Portland, Or., among many others. Images in the collection range in date from 1880 to 1951; most were taken circa 1900-1930.
The collection is organized into the following series:
Series A: Jackson family, 1880-1942
Series B: East Oregonian, Oregon Journal and related Images, circa 1887-1951
Series C: Oregon Journal buildings, 1912-circa 1950
Series D: People, unidentified, circa 1910-1920
The collection is open to the public.
Gift of Jackson Family, circa 1950s.
The Charles Samuel Jackson Papers, Mss 1389, are located in the Oregon Historical Society Research Library.
For more information on the Jackson family, see the Biography file in the Oregon Historical Society Research Library. The library's collection also includes books and pamphlets on the history of the Oregon Journal under the Jackson family's ownership.
The collection is indexed under the following headings in the online catalog. Researchers desiring materials about related topics, persons, or places should search the catalog using these headings:
Jackson, Charles Samuel, 1860-1924--Photographs; Jackson, Francis Clopton, 1887-1919--Photographs; Jackson, Maria Clopton, 1862-1956--Photographs; Jackson, Phillip Ludwell, 1893-1953--Photographs; Boychuk, Walter, 1886-1967
Jackson family--Photographs
Angelus Studio (Portland, Or.); United States. Army--World War, 1914-1918
United States. Navy--World War, 1914-1918
Merchant mariners--Photographs; Newspaper employees--Oregon--Photographs; World War, 1914-1918--Photographs
Pendleton (Or.)--Buildings, structures, etc.--Photographs; Portland (Or.)--Buildings, structures, etc.--Photographs; Portland (Or.)--Newspapers--Photographs
Photographs; Journalism
Photographic prints
- Jackson family, 1880-circa 1950; Series A; 108 items.
  The series is generally organized alphabetically, by family member.
  Includes portraits, professional photographs, and snapshots of Charles and Maria Jackson; their sons, Francis and Phillip; their grandson, Charles S. Jackson II; and Charles Jackson's brother, Moat. Snapshots include family, friends, automobile trips, and recreational activities, most unidentified as to location, names, and dates. Another group of snapshots documents Francis Jackson's service with the Merchant Marines during World War I. Others who are pictured with family members include Henry Thiele, prominent Portland restaurateur and caterer, and Blanche Sweet, actress.
  - Jackson, Charles Samuel (1860-1924), 1880-circa 1905; undated (Box-folder 1/1)
  - Jackson, Maria Clopton (1862-1956), 1936-circa 1950 (Box-folder 1/2)
    Includes photographs taken while serving as honorary vice-chairwoman of Democratic rally in Portland, Or., 1936; at her 80th birthday celebration in 1942; and at the Pendleton Round-Up circa 1950.
  - Jackson family, circa 1910-1927 (Box-folder 1/3)
    Includes photographs of a family automobile trip in Pennsylvania, circa 1910, as well as photographs of Charles S. Jackson, Charles S. Jackson II, Francis Jackson, and Maria Clopton Jackson.
  - Jackson, Charles Samuel (1914-1947), circa 1914-1932 (Box-folder 1/4)
  - Jackson, Charles Samuel (1914-1947) and wife, circa 1940 (Box-folder 1/5)
  - Jackson, Francis Clopton (1887-1919)--Snapshots, circa 1905-1915 (Box-folder 1/6)
    Depicts mostly recreational activities, including automobile trips, camping, swimming, boating, and fishing.
  - Jackson, Francis Clopton (1887-1919)--Merchant Marines, circa 1918 (Box-folder 1/7)
  - Jackson, Moat, 1903 (Box-folder 1/8)
  - Jackson, Phillip Ludwell (1893-1953), circa 1900-1940 (Box-folder 1/9-1/12)
    Includes photographs of Phillip at Princeton University; snapshots taken on automobile and fishing trips, as well as foreign travel; with his wife, Ella Teeney Jackson; and photographs of his service with the United States Army during World War I.
- East Oregonian, Oregon Journal and related images, circa 1887-1951; Series B; 15 items.
  The series is arranged chronologically.
  This series documents the facilities of the East Oregonian in Pendleton and activities of and related to the Oregon Journal, including its relationship to KOIN radio station. Among the images are portraits of Billie Burke and Lillian Russell, autographed to Charles S. Jackson.
  - East Oregonian, Pendleton, Or., circa 1887 (Box-folder 1/14)
    Office (group includes Charles S. Jackson and Maria Clopton Jackson), composing room, and press room.
  - Group of women with one man in front of Oregon Journal office, circa 1905 (Box-folder 1/15)
  - Charles Samuel Jackson and Phillip Ludwell Jackson with Portland Commercial Club excursion, Walla Walla, Wash., 1911 (Box-folder 1/16)
  - Autographed portraits, 1912-1915; 1915 (Box-folder A/3)
    Includes photographs of Billie Burke autographed to Charles Samuel Jackson and Lillian Russell autographed: "To a Real Editor, Mr. Jackson, from Lillian Russell, 1915."
  - Oregon Journal staff picnic at Clear Creek, 1919 (Box-folder 1/17)
  - Oregon Journal dance at Cotillion Hall, circa 1920 (Box-folder A/3)
  - Phillip Ludwell Jackson with group signing agreement between KOIN Radio and the Oregon Journal, circa 1930 (Box-folder 1/18)
  - Sam Hill Memorial, Columbia River Highway, Or., circa 1925 (Box-folder 1/19)
  - Choate Webster receiving Sam Jackson Trophy at Pendleton Round-Up, Pendleton, Or., 1951 (Box-folder 1/20)
- Oregon Journal buildings, 1912-circa 1950; Series C; 22 items.
  This series includes images of the Oregon Journal Building at Yamhill and Broadway in downtown Portland from construction to completion and one image of the Front Street building that supplanted it. The first building became known as the Jackson Tower after the Oregon Journal moved to Front Street in 1947.
  - Oregon Journal building (Yamhill and Broadway, Portland, Or.)--Construction, 1912 March-May (Box-folder 1/21)
    Includes architect's rendering.
  - Oregon Journal building--Completed, circa 1915-1920 (Box-folder 1/22)
  - Oregon Journal building--Front Street, Portland, Or., circa 1950 (Box-folder 1/23)
- Portraits, unidentified, circa 1910-1920; Series D; 5 items.
  - Women, circa 1910-1915 (Box-folder 1/24)
  - Group of men on steps of Multnomah County Library, Portland, Or., circa 1920 (Box-folder 1/25)